The Man... The Music... The Madness... The Murder... The Motion Picture.
Amadeus is a history, music, drama film directed by Miloš Forman.
Disciplined Italian composer Antonio Salieri becomes consumed by jealousy and resentment towards the
hedonistic and remarkably talented young Salzburger composer Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart.
Antonio Salieri, played by F. Murray Abraham.
Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, played by Tom Hulce.
Constanze Mozart, played by Elizabeth Berridge.
Emanuel Schikaneder, played by Simon Callow.
Leopold Mozart, played by Roy Dotrice.
Katerina Cavalieri, played by Christine Ebersole.
Amadeus is a 1984 American period drama film directed by Miloš Forman.
Peter Shaffer adapted it from his 1979 stage play, inspired by
Alexander Pushkin's 1830 play Mozart and Salieri.
Shaffer described it as a "fantasia on [a real-life] theme", as it imagines a rivalry between two
18th-century Vienna composers, Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart (Tom Hulce) and Antonio Salieri (F.
Murray Abraham).
Salieri struggles to reconcile his professional admiration and jealous hatred for Mozart,
and resolves to ruin Mozart's career as his form of vengeance against God.
Amadeus received its world premiere in Los Angeles on September 6, 1984.
It was released by Orion Pictures thirteen days later to widespread critical
acclaim and box office success, grossing over $90 million.
It was nominated for 53 awards and won 40, including 8 Academy Awards (including Best Picture), four
BAFTA Awards, and four Golden Globe Awards (including Best Motion Picture – Drama).
Abraham and Hulce were both nominated for the Academy
Award for Best Actor, with Abraham winning.
In 1998, the American Film Institute ranked it 53rd on its 100 Years...
100 Movies list.
In 2019, the film was selected for preservation in the United States National Film Registry by the
Library of Congress as being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
The film explores themes of opera, composer, musician, marriage crisis, italy.
The tone is emotional.